<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A case of conscience, concerning flying in times of trouble. Resolved according to the Scriptures, and the examples of holy men. Applyed to the present times and occasions. Imprimatur. Edm. Calamy.</title>
            <author>Torshell, Samuel, 1604-1650.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94755</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1934</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E65_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23308</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871960</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871960</idno>
            <idno type="VID">124379</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94755)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 124379)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 11:E65[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A case of conscience, concerning flying in times of trouble. Resolved according to the Scriptures, and the examples of holy men. Applyed to the present times and occasions. Imprimatur. Edm. Calamy.</title>
                  <author>Torshell, Samuel, 1604-1650.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Bellamie and Ralph Smith, and are to be sold at their shop, at the three golden Lions in Cornhill neare the royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy reads: "Aug: 16th".</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Moral and ethical aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:124379:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CASE OF CONSCIENCE, CONCERNING Flying in Times of Trouble.</p>
            <p>Reſolved According to the Scriptures, and the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Holy men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Applyed to the preſent times and occaſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi> Jmprimatur.</hi> Edm. Calamy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Bellamie</hi> and <hi>Ralph Smith,</hi> and are to be ſold at their ſhop, at the three golden Lions in <hi>Cornhill</hi> neare the royall Exchange. 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:124379:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:124379:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Bout foure moneths ſince, upon an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that offered it ſelfe, I then drew up this <hi>Caſe,</hi> ſo as it is. It was communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to divers private hands and had the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of ſome <hi>Divines</hi> both <hi>Learned</hi> and <hi>Conſcientious,</hi> yet <hi>I</hi> laid it by mee, being not deſirous to <hi>expoſe</hi> it (among the many <hi>Imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencies</hi> and unneceſſary and <hi>raw Scriblings</hi> now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes) to the publicke view. But now the <hi>opinion</hi> and <hi>requeſt</hi> of ſome who judge it <hi>uſefull</hi> hath obtained it to the <hi>preſſe:</hi> for they ſay the <hi>condition</hi> of the <hi>times</hi> doth <hi>challenge</hi> it, wherein many ſeeme to be <hi>aſhamed</hi> of their former <hi>acquaintance</hi> with the <hi>great cauſe</hi> in hand; The truth is, many that came up to the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſenſe</hi> in the <hi>head</hi> of the <hi>Tyde,</hi> are willing to <hi>ſhrinke</hi> away in the <hi>Ebbe</hi> of things. There is a poore and low and narrow Spirit in very many who thought well of the <hi>Parliament</hi> onely ſo long as no body ſpake ill of it, or durſt speake out, if they thought otherwiſe, and
<pb facs="tcp:124379:3"/>loved it while they might be ſafe, and enjoy the worlds friendſhip, God will not honour himſelfe by ſuch <hi>ſelf-ſeekers;</hi> wee muſt bid a better <hi>price,</hi> before God will part with the <hi>rich commodity</hi> of <hi>Reformation;</hi> If we love the publicke cauſe, wee muſt not onely keepe it company in its <hi>health,</hi> but ſtand by it and comfort it in its <hi>faintings.</hi> Amd this is the purpoſe of the following <hi>diſcourſe,</hi> which <hi>I</hi> commend unto the bleſſing of the Almighty.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:124379:3"/>
            <head>A Caſe of Conſcience, concerning Flying in times of Trouble.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Scriptures</hi> are ſo cleare, and the conſent of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines</hi> ſo full, that it had not needed to have beene put to the Queſtion, <hi>Whether flight be lawfull in times of trouble and perſecution;</hi> but that ſome have beene too rigid, and others contrarily have chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged this liberty without all caution, or reſpect to any circumſtances. I ſhall therefore ſo examine the caſe, that conſcience may be ſetled, when to take the liberty which God hath allowed, and how to know when God hath ſhut up the way againſt us.</p>
            <p>There is a flight which ariſeth; Firſt, from the ſhame of ſinne, and from feare of publicke juſtice. Secondly, from an inward ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and trembling, cauſed alſo by guilt, and laid upon men as a puniſhment, as it was in the caſe of <hi>Cain.</hi> Thirdly, from weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, irreſolution, and unbeliefe, which prevailed upon the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> who for ſooke <hi>Peſus</hi> and fied. Fourthly, from meere humane prudence and forecaſt, in which the Prophet <hi>Jonah</hi> offended. But
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:124379:4"/>none of theſe are ſpoken unto, in the preſent queſtion, bu that which <hi>Aretius</hi> defines,
<note place="margin">Mutatio loci, mali praeſentis vitand, alibique melius deeendi gratia, ſuſcepta cumtimore Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mint. Bened. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. problem.</note> to be, <hi>A changing of place, to ſhun ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent evill, and more comfortably to live elſewhere, undertaken in the feare of the Lord:</hi> Which diſtinguiſheth it from all thoſe former kindes of either raſh or ſinfull flight.</p>
            <p>'Tis a queſtion that exerciſed the <hi>primitive Divines,</hi> for thoſe times being very terrible till <hi>Conſtantine</hi> ſetled peace in the Church, made the ſearch very neceſſary; as the ſad and violent and unſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led time that weare fallen upon, make it now.</p>
            <p>I finde the <hi>Antients</hi> divided, according to the different ſenſe they entertained of the Scriptures, whether <hi>lawfull</hi> to flye and leave or change ones ſtation, and if lawfull, whether <hi>permitted onely,</hi> and ſo <hi>lawfull onely</hi> and no more, or a duty commanded, and ſo <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſary</hi> alſo as a binding law.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in a tract that he wrote profeſſedly of this argument, altogether denies it to be lawfull to flye, or ſeemes to deny it.</p>
            <p>He contends,
<note place="margin">Matth. 10.23.</note> that when our Lord bid his Diſciples <hi>when they were perſecuted in one City to fiye into another;</hi> He onely gave them a ſpeciall allowance (or diſpenſation rather) then for a particular reaſon, that the progreſſe of the Goſpell might not be hindered, but preached and ſpread abroad in all Cities. But that now the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell is already propagated, wee are to ſtand unto the profeſſion of the faith received, and to keepe our ſtation. And that becauſe nothing comes to paſſe without Gods order, and we are all in Gods hand; it were unbeleefe, treachery, cowardiſe, rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God to goe out of our place; and that we muſt dye in our ſtanding, and (if God will have it ſo) periſh in the ruines of our Country.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe he wrote; yet I expreſſe my ſelfe thus favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably of him, that he altogether denies flight to be lawfull, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſeemes to deny it;</hi> becauſe though moſt conceive that to be his very opinion, and the <hi>Antients</hi> condemned him for it, and <hi>Jerome</hi> in particular cenſures him,
<note place="margin">Hieron. lib. de Script. Illuſtr.</note> that when he wrote that booke hee had forſaken the ſound faith, and was gone over to the part of <hi>Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> the <hi>Heretique,</hi> and therefore wrote that booke in hatred, and diſgrace of the Chriſtians whoſe uſuall practiſe many of them was to decline the fury of the times where they might conveniently, though otherwiſe ambitious enough of <hi>martyrdome:</hi> yet I am not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:124379:4"/>wholly convinced to the contrary, but that perhaps writing to <hi>Fabius</hi> who was a <hi>presbyter</hi> and a <hi>paſtor</hi> of a Church, he might uſe that ſevere and rigid language to keepe and hold him upon his charge, in that dangerous and uncomfortable condition of things. But if it were truely his opinion, I conſent to the judgement of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine</hi> againſt him, and to the anſwers they directed to his arguments: That 'tis true, all things are ordered by God, and all are in his hand; yet <hi>David</hi> knew all this, but he fled not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding from the violence of <hi>Saul.</hi> And that God cals ſome to give teſtimony to the truth by death, others hee reſerves, and whom he ſaves from the rage of cruell ones he ſaves by meanes. If he ſhut up any man, it is his will and order hee ſhould ſtand the triall couragiouſly; but if hee offer an opportunitie and open the dore of eſcape, it is his will and ordering to eſcape. And to this very effect, <hi>Origen</hi> had formerly reſolved;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Origen</hi> in John.</note> 
               <q>That a man muſt main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Chriſts cauſe by death when he is taken, but before hee be taken, he may eſcape if honourably he can do it.</q>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Naz. in Orat.</hi> 10</note> And this was it for which <hi>Nazienzen</hi> commended <hi>Caeſarius</hi> that excellent Chriſtian; <q>That hee honorably yeelded to the times, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther betrayed the truth nor provoked danger.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not need to inſiſt upon this, the lawfulneſſe of declining danger; It is a dictate of nature, which grace alſo cheriſheth, and God hath planted a naturall love of life in every man, which teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him to ſhun what may bee harmefull. <hi>Tertullian</hi> (for ought I know) ſtands alone, againſt the lawfulneſſe; all the doubt among others is, whether it be a permiſſion onely or a precept.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and ſome others that goe in the middle and moderate way; doe ſay,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.12.</note> that God would have no man pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume of his ſtrength, for let him that ſtands take heed leſt hee fall; &amp; therefore as wel knowing our infirmitie, he gives us the ſame and as large allowance and liberty as he granted to his Diſciples, whom he permitted to flee from one Citie to another. There are ſome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of late that have held it but a permiſſion, and therefore ſay, that when our Saviour had given the immediate ſigne of the ruine of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and thereupon warned them to flie, <hi>when yee ſee the Abomination of deſolation, then let them that are in Judea flee unto the mountaines:</hi> He meant not to injoyne it as duety, but onely would thereby manifeſt the greatneſſe of the calamitie upon their Citie, and ſhew what they might doe in that caſe, and what they would be conſtrained to doe.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:124379:5"/>
            <p>Thirdly, but <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and others are expreſſe for it as a dutie; and that men muſt flie, when God calls them to flie. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> wrote two bookes of <hi>Apologie</hi> upon this argument, in both which he goes that way. And agreeable to this was the reſolution of <hi>Clement</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Clem. Strom.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.</note> that they are guiltie of their owne death that doe not avoid danger where they may. And accordingly <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> (who yet was afterwards himſelfe a <hi>Martry</hi>) perſwades flight, and tells them of <hi>Carthage,</hi> that it ſhall be reckoned as a martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, if any lawfully and worthily flying, doe miſcarry by wild beaſis, famine, or theeves. I confeſſe I encline to this, that it is a duety to provide for ſafetie by flight where it may be; but I will not interpoſe, becauſe the difference is not much materiall, for if it be lawfull, it is not much to me, whether onely permitted, or commanded.</p>
            <p>Having ſaid thus much, more generally, I ſhall conſider the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie in particular, as it concernes; firſt, other people; ſecondly, Miniſters and Paſtors.</p>
            <p>Firſt, concerning people that are of a private condition, 'tis out of all doubt that they may lawfully flie. We have many warranted examples of it in holy <hi>Scripture,</hi> among ſuch as were godly and conſcientious. <hi>David</hi> oft times layd hold upon this remedy, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares all along in his ſtory,
<note place="margin">1 Sam 21.1.22.1.27.1.</note> while he was in or belonging to the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Saul.</hi> So the faithfull were ſcattered upon the perſecution of <hi>Steven, Act.</hi> 8.1. and the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in that <hi>Catalogue</hi> of eminent men in the faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. reckons up many that in hard times forſooke their habitations, and expoſed themſelves to wants and extreame povertie, <hi>They wandred about in Sheepes-skins and Goat-skins, being deſtitute, afflicted, tormented, ver.</hi> 37. and unto ſolitary wandrings in voluntary exile; <hi>They wandred in deſarts, and in mountaines, and in dens and caves of the earth, verſ.</hi> 38. and all this to avoyd the fury of the times, as appeares, <hi>verſ.</hi> 36.37. <hi>Others had tryall of cruell mockings and ſcourgings, of bonds and impriſonments, they were ſtoned, they were ſawen aſunder, they were ſlaine with the Sword.</hi> Theſe evils overtaking others, the men whom the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> commends, provided to ſcape them by their wandring away into Deſerts. It were eaſie to bee large in <hi>inſtances</hi> in the ten <hi>primitive perſecutions.</hi> And of later times, we have freſher examples of our owne in <hi>Queene Maries</hi> time, that fled into other parts, and ſince of ſuch as from thoſe parts of <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> have fled to us. It were to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:124379:5"/>trifle, to ſpend more words for the proofe of this; but there are two things more neceſſary here to be done. Firſt to put in caution leſt ſome may haply preſume too farre upon this libertie, ſo law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Secondly, to make application of the queſtion to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time and condition of things, whether now bee the time to flie, whether now it be lawfull.</p>
            <p>Firſt the <hi>caution</hi> I would put in is this, that all <hi>Lay-people</hi> (for ſo I muſt all them for diſtinction, that I may be underſtood, not that I will juſtifie the word of difference) are not at libertie, if they bee bound up by office, relation, publique ingagement, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>No man may flie till the doore be ſet open unto bim,</hi> that is, not till all others doores of remedy be ſhut up: not till all hath beene done for maintenance of publique ſafetie and libertie, and for the oppoſing of evill and corruption: But when as water that hath broken downe the damme, there is no reſiſtance, then the dutie is to doe what may be to eſcape drowning. It lyeth upon all in ſome meaſure or other, to ſee to the ſtate of others ſafetie, eſpecially the publique. So that that which at all times elſe is lawfull, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move ones ſtation for better accommodating his trade and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſing, yet is not ſo, if any notable diſcouragement ariſe thence to the publique. This is grounded upon that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon bond of duty which lies mutually upon one and other in regard of vicinitie or neighbourhood of place. As from hence alſo it is, that rich men may not remove to their Country houſes in time of a publique peſtilence, till proviſion bee made and due care had of the poore, leſt they periſh for want of reliefe by their with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing.</p>
            <p>A man therefore may not ſlip away at a poſterne, hee muſt goe out that way which God ſets open, and he muſt have his paſſe. The Jewes had a direct open warrant, when they got away from <hi>Pharaoh, Exod.</hi> 13.21. And ſo had <hi>Joſeph</hi> when with <hi>Jeſus</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> he eſcaped into <hi>Egypt, Matth.</hi> 2.13. they were warned from heaven. But how ſhall we know we have a warrant? I can onely ſatisfie this, by conſidering ſome particular caſes recorded in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, wherein flight was warranted, that ſo we may make the better judgement upon our owne exigences.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I conceive it may be gathered from the ſtory in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.3.4. That <hi>Adhaerents</hi> may flie when the <hi>ſide</hi> it ſelfe is loſt. The <hi>Beerothites</hi> had aſſiſted the <hi>ſide</hi> and <hi>cauſe</hi> of <hi>Sauls houſe,</hi> to which they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:124379:6"/>were joyned in ſome relations, during all the warre, till it was ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly weakned and loſt, by the death of <hi>Abner,</hi> and then they fled to <hi>Gittaim.</hi> I know the inſtance doth not ſuite in all things, for they adhered to the <hi>worſer partie;</hi> yet howſoever it ſerves to my purpoſe, that they would have continued firme to the part if there had continued a <hi>head</hi> and <hi>conſiderable ſtrength</hi> to it; and left not the ſide, till they were left alone, and then they warrantably eſcaped, and not till then. The application is eaſie and ready to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent occaſions.</p>
            <p>Secondly, when a mans Relations and his calling are not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced by going out of the way, he may lawfully doe it; when his relations and preſent ſervice are not higher and more tender then his ſafetie. What was there in <hi>Jacobs family-relation,</hi> when as yet affaires did not depend upon him, that might be a blocke in his way of eſcape, when his mother ſent him farre off to <hi>Laban</hi> out of the reach of <hi>Eſau</hi>'s bloody attempts? <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.43.44.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, when the cauſe in which a man is inbarked is no way bettered by his ſtay, he may doe the ſame right to himſelfe, which he indeavoured to doe to it. Hence, when <hi>Jotham</hi> the youngeſt ſonne of <hi>Gideon,</hi> who had hardly eſcaped the conſpiracie of <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech,</hi> and underſtood the outrages of the new court and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thought it his dutie to make <hi>proteſtation</hi> againſt thoſe cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and to undeceive the people ſo farre as he might, when he had publiſhed his thoughts, he ran away, and fled to <hi>Beer, Judg.</hi> 9.21. for what advantage would it have beene to the cauſe, if he had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adviſedly verified his owne <hi>parable,</hi> and had been catched and torne by that <hi>Bramble?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, ſo that a man be ready to appeare when the houre of ſtanding requires, he may reſerve himſelfe till that houre of acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on come. Thus <hi>Moſes</hi> went aſide, <hi>Exod.</hi> 2.15. till buſineſſes were ripened. And <hi>Rutilius,</hi> in the eccleſiaſticall ſtory, often fled, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards became a Martyr; which was alſo the famous caſe of Saint <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Laſtly, if a man be ſingly hunted after for his eſtate and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, and no way be left him to keep himſelfe from injurious dealing, he may accommodate himſelfe elſewhere. For this reaſon <hi>Jacob</hi> conveyed himſelfe, and family, and eſtate, from under the hard and evill eye of <hi>Laban, Gen.</hi> 31.21. And it ſeemes by the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>Judg.</hi> 11.2.3. that <hi>Jephthah</hi> was thus neceſſitated to ſeeke an
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:124379:6"/>habitation in the Land <hi>Tob.</hi> But when (for inſtance) a <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary State</hi> is ingaged for the repreſſing of injuries, and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of publick liberties and mens eſtates, this alters the caſe and calls in all private thoughts of eſcape, to contribute them to the publick defence.</p>
            <p>More particulars might happily be obſerved of the Scripture, but becauſe they doe not occurre to my preſent meditations, this ſhall ſuffice for the firſt Caution.</p>
            <p>Firſt, As every one muſt have regard to ſome circumſtances, ſo if any one have beene more appearing, more forward, more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging in his ſpeeches and advices, and be a man look't at, he is to be more cautious. This I ſuppoſe was that which was meant by that ſpeech of <hi>Nehemiah, Neh.</hi> 6.11. <hi>Should ſuch a man as I flie?</hi> Yet I doubt not but if the flood had broken in upon him violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo that the fury of the Waters could not have beene kept back, he would have runne to avoid drowning; but it would have been in the <hi>Reere</hi> of the people. The Captaines place in a retreate is hindmoſt. Such as have gone before the people in a publicke un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, and have beene leading men, muſt ſee the people ſafe before him, before he give his ground.</p>
            <p>Secondly, But now for application to the preſent condition of things: What may wee ſay of this preſent time? <hi>Is the doore now open or not?</hi> I anſwer. Wee may not preſume to judge preciſely of the iſſue of things. But there are two things I have here to ſay.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That it is true, wee have many ſad <hi>omens</hi> of the ruine of our nation. As our Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> after all other warnings, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Calamities, foretold the deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 24.15. Luk. 21.21.</note> that they might know that deſolation was neere at hand, when they ſhould ſee the <hi>Abominatirn of Deſolation ſet up,</hi> or as <hi>S. Luke</hi> expreſſes it, <hi>Jeruſalem compaſſed with Armies:</hi> So hath God taken all the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and given all the warnings to us, which have beene uſuall before a Nation comes to deſtruction. All the ſinnes which are noted by <hi>Divines</hi> or <hi>Politicall writers</hi> to be the generall, Internall cauſes of ruine, doe notoriouſly ſhew themſelves among us; <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of enormous ſinnes,</hi> of the deepeſt ſtaine and the higheſt provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; <hi>The multitude of Sinners;</hi> and the <hi>impunity of ſinning.</hi> And then, what <hi>warnings</hi> have we had, nay what have wee not had? And after all, beſides the dangerous <hi>diſtemper</hi> ſpread over all our body, the diſcord in our owne bowells, an <hi>abominable Army, Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:124379:7"/>Enſignes,</hi> the <hi>Romiſh Banner,</hi> doth alſo portend the worſt of evills. If I ſhould alſo touch at thoſe <hi>Periods,</hi> which <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>great Authors</hi> doe ſo much diſcourſe of, and which they will have to be finiſhed in this age; I ſhould reckon up enough, to make us caſt about at leaſt in caſe things ſhould come to extremity. I am miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the ſtory, if the believers had not an eye to <hi>Pella,</hi> even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Titus</hi> came, and conveyed ſome things away. I obſerve this from that paſſage in <hi>Eccleſ:</hi> Hiſtory, of S. <hi>James</hi> his <hi>chayre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, But in the next place, I am not willing to leave theſe ſad thoughts upon any, and doe therefore obſerve that there are two maine conſiderations, wherein the condition of <hi>our nation</hi> differs from that of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> at that time. Firſt, one is, that they had an immediate warning of ruine by a direct ſigne which they might clearely take notice of. But ſo have not wee. Secondly, the other is, That there was an inevitable and irrevocable ſentence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> but for our nation we are to thinke, according to what the Scripture ſpeakes,
<note place="margin">Jer. 18.7.8.</note> 
               <q>That at what inſtant God ſpeakes of a Kingdome to pluck up and deſtroy, if that nation againſt whom God hath pronounced, turne from their evill, he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of the evill that he thought to doe unto them.</q> Theſe are the things that maintaine in us ſome hope, beſides the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage</hi> and the feare of the Lord, which hath beene given and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued of late to many, who have ventured themſelves upon the great cauſe now in hand, and are conſtant to it.</p>
            <p>But what then may be the Reſolution? I anſwere, P. <hi>Martyr</hi> when he had eſcaped from <hi>Luca</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> wrote back againe to his <hi>Auditors</hi> there, and in particular to a friend, about the <hi>Caſe</hi> of <hi>flying;</hi> wherein he ſeemes not to me to be determining, (for the circumſtances of every mans condition doe ſo differ that it is very difficult to make a ſetled rule) but adviſeth to <hi>pray</hi> unto God for direction, and after prayer, as they find their hearts enclined, ſo to <hi>flye</hi> or <hi>ſtay.</hi> This Counſell I doe approve, to ſeeke <hi>Counſell</hi> from God; but to take the next inclination of heart, to be the preſent an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, I beleeve may be unſafe. The direction is too large, too un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine. Beſides that many cannot, haply, diſcerne clearely, many may deceive themſelves about the inclination of heart, which wee finde ordinarily to be ſtrongly <hi>biaſſed</hi> by private reſpects and <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſes.</hi> Wee muſt looke further then our proper inclinations, yea further then our proper convenience and advantages, to obſerve
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:124379:7"/>how things are round about us, and whether there be any thing in the publicke, wherein we are concerned, and that will coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termand our proper inclination, and prevaile above our proper convenience. And if I may expreſſe my conceit, Things ſtand now in ſuch poſture, that God requires our deep engagement, and that wee ſhould baniſh all thoughts of declining. In this great hazard that liberty, lawes, and religion run, to leave our ground, were to leave <hi>Popery Maſter</hi> of the <hi>Field.</hi> Wee may not now ſuffer the thoughts of ſafety elſewhere, to womanize our ſpirits: but together with our earneſt and humble prayers for our <hi>King,</hi> that he may at length embrace the Counſells of our great Eſtate; wee are in caſe of ſo ſad a neceſſity, to reſolve to lay out all our ſtrength towards the great buſineſſe, and rather <hi>burne</hi> our <hi>ſhips,</hi> as ſome ſtories mention of ſome reſolute Souldiers, to keep off all thoughts of returne in the cowardly and faint-hearted; that is, forget all conveniences and opportunities of being elſewhere in a whole skinne.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Having thus farre ſpoken of the liberty of other people, It remaines to be examined whether Miniſters the Paſtors of Congregations be at the ſame liberty. I finde the <hi>Antients</hi> and others more difficult concerning them, urging that place of Chriſt, <hi>Job.</hi> 10.12, 13. <q>Hee that is an hireling, ſeeth the Woolfe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and leaveth the ſheepe and fleeth. The hireling fleeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is an hireling, and careth not for the ſheepe.</q> And it is not without reaſon that they are ſtraight towards them; for Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters are to have care not ſo much of their owne <hi>Bodies</hi> as of the <hi>Soules</hi> of others. Their mouth is the <hi>dug</hi> on which they hang and feed; and many build on their example. Who ſhall looke to the <hi>flocke,</hi> if the <hi>Shepheard</hi> be gone? Who ſhall governe the <hi>Ship</hi> in a ſtorme, if the <hi>Pilot</hi> be not at the <hi>Sterne?</hi> Who ſhall prevent the theife, if there be no <hi>watchman?</hi> The people doe at all times need their Paſtors, but moſt of all when the dangers are greateſt. There is uſe of a Pylot in the calme, much more when the weather is ſtormie. What will the Shepheard of the peoples ſoules anſwer to the great Shepheard? Theſe conſiderations wrought effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſtrongly upon many of the old Paſtors of the Church, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of whom ſealed up their profeſſion with their blood; and preached their doctrines over againe in Martyrdome. <hi>Peter</hi> was
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:124379:8"/>willingly crucified with his feete upward. <hi>James</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> dyed by the ſword. <hi>Ignatius</hi> derided all torments. <hi>Polycarpus, Juſtin, Cyprian,</hi> of old; <hi>Cranmer, Latimer, Ridley, Hooper, Farrar, Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, Saunders, Taylor, Rogers,</hi> of late, and many others, laid downe their lives for the brethren in the Teſtimony of <hi>Jeſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.16. <hi>Euſeb. hiſt. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c</hi> 35.</note> And contrarily it remaines as a blot upon the name of <hi>Novatus</hi> in the Eccleſiaſticall hiſtory, who being a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> in a time of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution left his flocke, and diſclaimed his office.</p>
            <p>All this is true, and true it is that ſuch cannot be too abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cautelous; yet ſome there are that have ſtretched theſe argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments too farre, as if it were unlawfull in any caſe, for a Miniſter who is faſtned to any particular congregation to flye. And they have made an obſervation, how true I know not, neither have I opportunity to examine or diſprove it; That in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes among all thoſe Schollers and Divines that fled, there were none but <hi>fellowes</hi> of <hi>Colledges,</hi> and <hi>Students</hi> in <hi>Divinity,</hi> ſuch as had undertaken no paſtorall charge; but that all the <hi>Bps.</hi> and ſetled paſtors that were good, continued upon their charge, with reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to welcome the aſſault when it ſhould come. Which whether it may be good I doubt; or if it may be, yet it will but onely diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>that that was the received reſolution then, which might haply be too rigid in ſome caſes: for though a Miniſter be ſpecially bound up, if by his flight, the glory of God, the Church, the cauſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, the ſoules of the people, ſhal receive any prejudice: yet in ſome caſes they may flye, according to the warrantable examples of <hi>Elias</hi> the Prophet, of our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> who often with-drew himſelfe during the yeares of his publicke miniſtry; and left a word of direction, at leaſt of allowance, for thoſe whom he ſent to preach, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.23. The <hi>Diſciples,</hi> Act. 8.1. and Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Act. 9. made uſe of this lawfull liberty.</p>
            <p>There are five doores, (if not more) through which even the Miniſter of a Congregation may paſſe in his flight, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtayed by any ſuch queſtion from God,
<note place="margin">Gen. 16.8.</note> as was once put to <hi>Hagar</hi> by an <hi>Angel, Whence cameſt thou? and whither wilt thou goe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, when there is a <hi>Diſperſion</hi> of the whole flocke, there is no doubt but the ſhepheard may alſo eſcape. There ſeemes to have beene ſuch a generall diſperſion of the whole <hi>Church</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> upon that great perſecution that was raiſed after <hi>Steven</hi> was ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.1. This is clearely the caſe of many Miniſters of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:124379:8"/>whoſe congregations have beene wholly ſcattered, if not maſſacred. And ſome places in this Kingdome, have felt well neare a like violence.</p>
            <p>Secondly, when the perſecution is particular, and the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not aimed at, or not ſo directly concerned.
<note place="margin">1 King 19.3.</note> It was the caſe of <hi>Elias,</hi> and clearely of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> newly upon his converſion which much enraged his old companions, friends, and maſters,
<note place="margin">Act. 9.23.</note> ſo that him they ſought, the Church at <hi>Damaſcus</hi> being ſafe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Athan.</hi> Apol. 2.</note> how elſe could <hi>Ananias</hi> and the brethren ſtay there? <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in his ſecond, which is his large <hi>Apologie,</hi> makes it appeare by a full relation, that he lay under a private particular and extreame hatred, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore might ſafely and with a good conſcience leave his charge to eſcape the traps and ſnares of the <hi>Arrian Biſhops,</hi> his enemies,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide etiam Buxtorf. in Abrev. Hebr. p.</hi> 165, 166. <hi>De R. Simeone.</hi>
               </note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was ſo thoroughly the truths friend.</p>
            <p>This particular danger will warrant an eſcape, when there is but a ſtrong preſumption of it, though no actuall attempt. When <hi>Chriſt</hi> knew that there was a <hi>conſultation</hi> among the <hi>Phariſees</hi> how to deſtroy him, he withdrew himſelfe.
<note place="margin">Matth. 12.15.</note> At another time when he perceived that the envy was encreaſed againſt him, becauſe many came in to his <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> and ſo his name being growne up would and did endanger him, he left <hi>Judaea</hi> and departed into <hi>Galile.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 4.3.</note> Nay when he ſaw by their dealing with others what himſelfe muſt looke for, when he heard that <hi>John</hi> was beheaded,
<note place="margin">Matth. 14.12.13.</note> he departed by ſhip into a deſart place. The reverend <hi>Muſculus</hi> wrote after theſe copies. He was the Preacher at <hi>Anſpurg</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> where his zeale againſt Popery cauſed him to be ſo maliced, that hee was faine to be guarded to his <hi>pulpit</hi> ordinarily. When the booke of the <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim</hi> a <hi>mixture</hi> of <hi>Religions</hi> was ſent by the <hi>Emperour Charles</hi> the fifth and received by the Citie, <hi>Muſculus</hi> who could not preach in better times without danger, knew well enough there would then be no biding for him, and therefore before further proſecution got away.</p>
            <p>I the rather inſtance in this caſe ſo warranted by examples, becauſe it will come home and cloſe to the caſe of many able and laborious miniſters, who from ſeverall parts of the Kingdome, have beene carried by their juſt and grounded feares from their houſes and Congregations, whom many prophane ſcoffers who know how to deride but not compaſſionate their miſery, brand for <hi>cowards</hi> and <hi>runawayes,</hi> and having forced them to flie, after rayle at them
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:124379:9"/>for flying. I thought fit to inſert this by the way, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and the clearing of thoſe upon whom their ſuffrings by the <hi>Cavalierie</hi> in one kind or other, hath put the name of <hi>plundred Miniſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Under this head I adde, that a miniſter may flie from a ſudden popular attempt and fury. Thus Chriſt did when thoſe of the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue</hi> of <hi>Nazareth</hi> would have throwne him downe headlong from the brow of an hill.
<note place="margin">Luk. 4.30.</note> In ſuch a danger one may run even out of the pulpit;
<note place="margin">Joh. 8.59</note> ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> at another time, when the people in ſtead of giving attention fell to throw ſtones at him, he ſlipt out of the pulpit.
<note place="margin">Act. 14.6.</note> And it appeares by the ſtory, that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> were in the actuall exerciſe of their miniſtry, when they fled from <hi>Iconi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> to <hi>Lyſtra.</hi> It was even out of the Synagogue.</p>
            <p>And laſtly let me note this alſo that ſuch a particular perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and danger, will authoriſe and warrant even an uncomely eſcape, and plead for ſuch actions as otherwiſe and at other times would be unhandſome and unworthy of the dignitie of ſo weightie a calling.
<note place="margin">Act. 9.23.</note> Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> getting over the <hi>towne wall,</hi> yea his <hi>Basket</hi> will be juſtified by this. <hi>Muſculus</hi> (of whom I ſpake before) when he ſlipt from <hi>Auſpurg,</hi> left his wife and eight children for a while without any notice whither he was gone. But moſt nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is that paſſage of the learned <hi>Divine, John Brentius.</hi> He was in great danger becauſe of the <hi>Interim.</hi> The <hi>Emperour</hi> was ſo exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated that he commanded hee ſhould be brought to him alive or dead. The <hi>Commiſſary</hi> comes to <hi>Hale</hi> in <hi>Saxonie,</hi> where <hi>Brentius</hi> preacht, calls the Senate and tooke an oath of them not to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his deſigne. But it happened by the good providence of God, that one <hi>Alderman</hi> came in, after the oath was taken, undiſcerned; and hearing the plot, had onely time to convey away a ſhort note with theſe words; <hi>Fuge, fuge Brenti, cito, citius, citiſſimè. Flee, flee Bren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, in haſt, haſt, poſt-haſt. Brentius</hi> tooke the warning, diſguiſed himſelfe like a <hi>Captaine,</hi> with <hi>Buffe,</hi> and a <hi>patch</hi> upon one eye: and in that habit ſecured himſelfe. And is excuſed by the grave writer of his ſtory; which I alſo alleadge in defence of thoſe <hi>Scarlet cloaks, Buffe-coates, gray rockets, perukes</hi> of <hi>hayre,</hi> and <hi>coloured montero's,</hi> which have of late hid many grave and ſober Miniſters from the eyes of their adverſaries.</p>
            <p>I proceed to the third particular, no Miniſter is bound up, when it is not for the good of the Church that he ſhould ſtay, but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:124379:9"/>haply much better for it that he eſcape. Suppoſe that all the darts are aimed at one breaſt, and an offer be made, give up ſuch an head and all the reſt ſhall be quiet; or it be knowne that if one be removed, all the reſt ſhall be ſecured; In this caſe, <hi>Divines</hi> have held, that greater ſervice may be done by abſence and flight, then by ſtay. <hi>Cyprian</hi> profeſſeth he went aſide,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cypr. Epiſt.</hi> 15.</note> for the benefit of the <hi>Church</hi> at <hi>Carthage.</hi> And <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> ſatisfies his friends in <hi>Italy</hi> by this, after he had left <hi>Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en</hi> and his dignity there. Hee writes back to them; <q>That he could not have ſtayed with them, but he had beene ſilenced and ill uſed, and that no way to their good, but he ſhould have made them more obnoxious, and looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with a narrower and more curious eye by their adverſaries. And leſt they ſhould object; But why did you not ſtay till it came to extremity? He tells them, That he found it was the opportunity that God directed them unto. That he was uſefull where he now was, but with them he could not be ſo. He could not have enjoyed liberty to doe there what he would, about their reformation, but in ſtriving to ſhew them truth, he ſhould have wronged them of their peace. But now they might have peace, and his helpe too, that is, by his letters and ſecret directions to them. And finally he promiſed to returne to them againe, if ever the doore ſhould be opened, and it were likely he might ſtay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them without hazarding of them.</q> Thus that reverend and godly man, ſatisfied himſelfe and them. And by this another e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent perſon ſatisfied the world. The perſon that I meane, was that rare man, <hi>John Camera,</hi> the learned, powerfull and famous Preacher of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Church at <hi>Burdeaux</hi> in <hi>France.</hi> There was an ill ſpirited rotten man, one <hi>Santangelus</hi> a <hi>Lawyer</hi> that dwelt there, who would be taken for a Proteſtant, but was cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> or worſe, an <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> he cunningly brought it about, that the good man was forced to leave his charge, and then <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangelus</hi> boaſted that he was a Mercinary and fled when he ſaw the Woolfe come.
<note place="margin">Cameron. Stel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liteut. in San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tang.</note> 
               <hi>Camero</hi> was faine to publiſh an Apologie to the world, to cleare himſelfe of that ſtaine, and to ſhew how much the whole City was concerned in his removing. And did ſit ſo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfyingly and ſo to purpoſe, that all men tooke notice of the baſe frauds of that diſſembling Lawyer, and were convinced that out of conſcience he did that good ſervice to his City, by getting away to draw aſide after him the hatred conceived and intended againſt it.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:124379:10"/>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth dore for a Miniſters paſſage out is, when hee is endangered, and others are ſufficiently leſt to ſupply the care of the peoples ſoules. The Church received not detriment by <hi>Pauls</hi> flight, for it ſeemes <hi>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> was a teacher there, and was ſafe to inſtruct them, and haply others beſides him, and the Church flouriſhed. We have a pregnant inſtance to this purpoſe, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 26.20.21.</note> who propheſied in the name of the Lord, againſt the Citie and againſt the land, according to all the words of <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah;</hi> and when <hi>Jehojakim</hi> the King with his mightie men and the Princes heard his words, the King ſought to put him to death, but when <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ria<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> heard it, he ſearing fled, and went into <hi>Egypt.</hi> He preacht the ſame things that <hi>Jeremiah</hi> did; but it ſeemes at that time, the Court could better beare <hi>Jeremy</hi> then him, and <hi>Jeremy</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then for that ſeaſon ſafe, and in the exerciſe of his office, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riab</hi> provided for his preſent ſafetie,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 22.23.</note> (though afterwards he was taken and made a Martyr.)</p>
            <p n="5">5. Laſtly, I will mention but one other head, that it is lawfull for a Miniſter to flie when he hath the conſent of his Church. <hi>Paul</hi> beſides other warrants had this;
<note place="margin">Act. 9.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Act. 17.13.14.</note> The Diſciples let him downe by the wall in a Basket. And when the Jewes of <hi>Theſſalonica</hi> came to intrap <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Berca,</hi> immediatly the Brethren ſent him away, to goe as it were by Sea.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cyp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Epiſt.</hi> 6.</note> Thus <hi>Cyprian</hi> went aſide, by the conſent, yea the entreatie of the people of <hi>Carthage,</hi> and by the <hi>adviſe</hi> of <hi>Tertullus</hi> who was a <hi>presbyter</hi> of prime and great authoritie. <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus</hi> though hee departed from <hi>Auſpurg</hi> in great diſtraction, yet came and told the <hi>Conſull</hi> or <hi>Major</hi> before he went, and had (as I gather) a <hi>diſmiſſion.</hi> But <hi>Philip Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> makes it moſt evident con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his reverend father, <hi>D. David Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> of <hi>Heidleberg</hi> in the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinate,</hi> that in the late popiſh warres againſt that Country which is now made deſolate, when they knew a <hi>ſiege</hi> would bee laid to <hi>Heidleberg,</hi> the Citizens were ſo tender of him, that they adviſed, yea intreated him to be gone.</p>
            <p>This is that I have to ſay concerning the lawfull freedomes of the miniſters of the word, and concerning the whole caſe, when it may be lawfull for any to flie, and when not. Let me ſhut up this diſcourſe with a word of Application. I hope wee have not need of this caſe, and that God will ſo farre magnifie his grace towards us of this poore ſinfull nation that we ſhall have no need of it, and this is in all my prayers; yet becauſe we know not unto what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:124379:10"/>we may be reſerved, let us get our conſciences rightly ſetled in ſo neceſſary, ſo conſiderable a point. Wee walke moſt ſafely, when we walke after counſell. And if we thus walke, and are obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent unto the Counſells of the Lord, we may have comfort, though we be forced to flie; and may refreſh our ſelves with that ſweet place of the pſalme, <hi>Thou telleſt</hi> (or numbreſt) <hi>my wandrings,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 56.8.</note> put thou my teares into thy bottle; are they not in thy booke?</hi> But what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort can there be, if we runne away from a good cauſe, as if wee were aſhamed to <hi>owne,</hi> or afraid to <hi>aſſiſt it,</hi> and unwilling to ſuffer and be loſt with it. <hi>Chriſt</hi> tels us that his Diſciples muſt (if the cauſe ſo require it) even <hi>hate their owne lives.</hi> And that <hi>he that ſaves his life ſhall loſe it.</hi> And truely that man is not ſafe, though hee ſaves his skin, that is not mindfull and regardfull to ſave his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward peace. Let us ſtay or flie, as the counſell of God ſhall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect us; elſe if wee bee found running from God, wee may bee overtaken with <hi>Jonah</hi> in a tempeſt, and fall into the <hi>Sea,</hi> and bee ſwallowed of the <hi>Whale.</hi> Oh how would it ſinke a man when his conſcience ſhould anſwer him ſome ſad queſtions in a ſtrange land, <hi>I have left my houſe and habitation, have I not left God too?</hi> Yes, <hi>thou haſt alſo left God by an unbeleeving haſt.</hi> I am deprived of my land, and my goods, and my ſtate: <hi>Have I not loſt my peace too?</hi> Yes, <hi>Thou haſt loſt thy peace, through thy wary providence to ſhift for thy ſelfe, in the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of the publique which ought to bee dearer to thee then thy ſelfe.</hi> Oh let us baniſh all thoughts of flying, when God calls us to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſervice. And if we aſſiſt him when he pleaſeth to honour us in accepting our ſervice, he will either open a dore in the greateſt need, or hide us in the evill day, or turne the worſt of evils to our good.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
